Guide to the Myron Taylor papers, 1938-1952
Taylor, Myron papers, 1938-1952
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Myron Taylor papers, 1938-1952.
3308
Myron Charles, Taylor 1874-1959.
8 cubic ft.; 1 o/s vol.; 2 map case folders.
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, statements, clippings.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, statements, and clippings relating to Taylor's service as personal representative of President Truman to Pope Pius XII and U.S. Ambassador on Special Missions.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Industrialist, diplomat, lawyer.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, statements, and clippings relating to Taylor's service as personal representative of President Truman to Pope Pius XII and U.S. Ambassador on Special Missions. Includes material relating to the refugee situation in Europe, 1938-47, and to meetings of Protestant clergymen with Taylor in New York City, October 1947 and May 1949. Correspondents include Harry S. Truman and Pope Pius XII.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Taylor, Myron Charles, 1874-1959.; Pius XII, Pope, 1876-1958.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.
Subjects:
Diplomatic and consular service, American.; Refugees--Europe--1938-1947.; Papacy--History--20th century.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- "Extra sets of 'Correspondence between Pres. Truman and Pope' as it was originally set up and before any extractions were made resulting from objections to publication of specific pieces of correspondence." REB. Feb. 1953 (envelop) (Box 1)
- Correspondence between President Harry S. Truman, His Holiness Pope Pius XII and Hon. Myron Taylor, 1945-1949 (3 binders, 1 typescript and 2 carbon copies) (Box 1)
- Title as above but contains photocopy of handwritten letter, Aug. 31, 1945, from Pope Pius XII to Myron Taylor (2 binders, both are carbon typescript books) (Box 1)
- Exchange of letters between His Excellency Harry S. Truman, President of the United States of America, and His Holiness Pope Pius XII, 1946-1952 (2 binders, the original typescript is incomplete) (Box 1)
- Correspondence between President Truman and His Holiness Pope Pius XII, 1945-1949 (1 binder, actually the dates in this volume are Sept. 17, 1941-Jan. 18, 1950) (Box 1)
- Loose carbon copies of drafts of letter, Dec. 1949, which Myron presented to His Holiness the Pope (drafts by Harley Notter, approved by William D. Hassett, Secretary to the President) (Box 1)
- Bombing of Rome, 1942-1943 (4 binders, all appear to contain different material) (Box 1)
- Memoranda regarding Vatican Mission, Oct. 20, 1949 (Box 1)
- Mr. Myron Taylor's Mission to the Vatican, Nov. 1949-Dec. 1949 (3 binders) (Box 1)
- Report to the President by Mr. Myron Taylor on his European Trip, July 22, 1950-Sept. 5, 1950 (5 binders) (Box 1)
- Title as above with material of 1950-1951 added (1 binder) (Box 1)
- Mission of Honorable Myron Taylor, May 1951-July 1951 (4 binders) (Box 1)
- Germany (2 binders, original typescript and carbon copy; latter has penciled notes) (Box 1)
- Germany, submitted to Mr. Myron C. Taylor (2 binders, these are letters to MCT, 1942) (Box 1)
- Recommendations for Retention of Steel Capacity in Western Germany (1 binder, photocopies of reports, charts, etc.) (Box 1)
- Italy (1 binder, original letters, carbons, news clippings, etc. 1943) (Box 1)
- Memoranda on Italy from Myron Taylor, Jan. 13, 1943(1 binder) (Box 1)
- Peace with Italy, May 1943-Aug. 1943 (3 binders, carbon typescripts) (Box 1)
- Confidential correspondence from the Prime Minister of Italy to Honorable Myron Taylor, Jan. 29, 1948 (1 binder, carbon typescript) (Box 1)
- Memoranda pertaining to Hon. Myron Taylor's visits to Portugal and Spain, 1941-1943 as the President's personal representative to His Holiness Pope Pius XII (4 binders) (Box 1)
- Secret memoranda on European political and religious situation, 1941-1946, from Mr. Myron Taylor, Oct. 26, 1946, Vol. II. (2 binders, both carbon typescripts) (Box 1)
- Title as above, but dated Dec. 30, 1946 (2 binders, both carbon typescripts) (Box 1)
- Supplemental memoranda regarding religious and political situations in Albania, Czechoslavakia, Poland, Rumania, and Yugoslavia. From Myron Taylor, Nov. 6, 1947 (3 binders, all carbon typescript) (Box 1)
- Memoranda concerning religious and political situations in Czechoslavakia, Poland, and Rumania. From Myron Taylor, Jan. 29, 1948 (1 binder) (Box 1)
- Memoranda concerning religious and political situations in Europe, 1946-1948, from Myron Taylor, Mar. 24, 1948 (1 binder) (Box 1)
- Secret memoranda on European political and religious situation, 1941-1946, from Myron Taylor, Sept. 4, 1956, Vatican, Czechoslavakia, Germany, Hungry, Italy, Poland, Rumania, Russia, Yugoslavia (1 binder) (Box 1)
- Title as above but also includes Austria, Oct. 29, 1946. Also includes 2 page typescript copy of "Extract from 'The Ciano Diaries'"[See special mission, 1950, letter to Churchhill, May 23, 1950] (1 binder) (Box 1)
- Trieste and Yugoslavia, 1946-1949 (1 binder) (Box 1)
- European Meetings, 1941 (1 binder) (Box 1)
- Report by Mr. Myron C. Taylor, personal representative of the President of the United States to His Holiness Pope Pius XII, 1940-1949 (Box 2)
- Documentation of the Mission of President Roosevelt to His Holiness Pope Pius XII by his personal respresentative, Myron C. Taylor, 1940-1945 (Box 2)
- As above but for President Truman, 1940-1945 (Box 2)
- Report by Mr. Myron C. Taylor, personal representative of the President of the United States on special mission, 1950-1952 (Box 2)
- Indexes of Mr. Myron Taylor's European missions for the President of the United States, 1940-1952 (3 copies, carbon typescripts) (Box 3)
- Chronological brief of Mr. Myron Taylor's European missions for the President of the United States, 1940-1952 (2 copies, carbon typescripts) (Box 3)
- Efforts toward religious cooperation for World Peace 1947-1952, Myron C. Taylor. (carbon typescript) (Box 3)
  This volume had typescript letters bound May 3, 1954, to the President from MCT regarding disposition of documents on missions to Pope Pius XII, 1940-1950. Has been in touch with Wayne Grover, Archivist of U.S.
- Extracts from books regarding the Activities of Myron C. Taylor, prepared by E.S. (2 copies, 1 original typescript and one carbon copy) (Box 3)
- Meetings of Protestant Clergymen with Myron C. Taylor at Union Club, Park Avenue and 69th Street, New York, Monday, Oct. 20, 1947and Tuesday May 3, 1949 (2 copies; 1 marked Mr. Taylor's copy which is said to be complete, other has apparently some pages deleted, see note in book) (Box 3)
- Summary of Contracts by Mr. Myron C. Taylor with leaders in religion, 1940-1953 (2 copies, carbon typescripts) (Box 3)
- Original letters of Cordell Hull (Sec. of State) to Myron Taylor, 1939-1954 (Box 4)
- Original letters of Monsignori Montini and Tardini to MCT, 1940-1956 (Box 4)
- Original letters of Sumner Wells, (under Secretary of State) to MCT, 1938-1956 (Box 4)
- Original letters of Winston Churchhill, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Herbert Hoover, Edward Stettinuis (Sec. of State) to MCT, 1932-1954 (Box 4)
- Original letters of Franklin D. Roosevelt to MCT, 1933-1945 (Box 4)
- Telegrams and letters (originals) to MCT in his appointemnt as personal representative of the President of the United States to His Holiness Pope Pius XII, Dec. 1939 (Box 4)
- Original letters of Harry S. Truman to MCT, 1947-1959 (Box 4)
- Original letters of His Holiness Pope Pius XII to MCT (Montinni and Tardini) and telegrams, 1948-1957 (Box 4)
- Student Board Yearbook, 1955-1956, of Cornell United Religious Work (Box 4)
- 3 volumes of photographs, all of the Vatican Mission, 1940-1946 (Box 5)
- 2 black loose leaf volumes - Titled Religous Books, both concerning correspondence and documentation relating to Mr. Taylor's contacts and meetings with Protestant leaders in Europe and America, 1947-1956 (Box 5)
- 1 book of photographs of Mr. Taylor's first audience with His Holiness Pope Pius XII (Box 5)
- 1 photograph of Mr. and Mrs. Harry Truman to institute Pius XII, Villa Schifanois, Florence, Italy, May 27, 1956 (Box 5)
- 3 blue loose-leaf notebooks (carbon typescripts) having yellow slip with title "Work Book. MCT's Contact with Leaders in Religion, 1940-1953" (Note in first one, "excepting His Holiness Pope Pius XII") (Box 6)
- Black loose volume (original and carbon typescripts) relating to contacts with various religious leaders, 1947-1953 (Box 6)
- Volume - luncheon by Myron C. Taylor, Hotel Excelsior, Rome, March 26, 1940 (All acceptances pasted in, refusals also) (Box 6)
- Volume - luncheon by Myron C. Taylor, Hotel Excelsior, Rome, The Vatican, in honor of His Eminence Cardinal Maglione, Secretary of State, Mar. 27, 1940 (Acceptances and refusals pasted in) (Box 6)
- Letters and other documents written by or concerning MCT, Sept. 1939-Apr. 1945, as the Franklin D. Roosevelt Library, Hyde Park, New York (5 binders, 2 original typescripts and 3 carbon typescripts) (Box 6)
- Religious representation, Feb. 27, 1951 (3 binders, carbon typescripts and Mr. Taylor's copy) (Box 6)
- Additional religious material, 1948-1949 (3 binders, all slightly different) (Box 6)
- Correspondence between Mr. Taylor and His Holiness Pope Pius XII, 1940-1950 (1 binder, incomplete) (Box 6)
- Correspondence between Mr. Taylor and His Holiness Pope Pius XII, 1947-1953 (1 binder) (Box 6)
- Christmas messages exchanged between Myron C. Taylor and His Holiness Pope Pius XII, Dec. 1940-Dec. 1948 (5 binders, 1 original typescript and 4 carbon typescripts) (Box 6)
- Letters regarding Mr. Taylor's appointment to the Intergovernmental Committee on Political Refugees and His Holiness Pope Pius XII, Apr. 1938-Mar. 1948 (1 binder) (Box 6)
- Presidential letters of instruction to Ambassador Myron C. Taylor, 1950-1952, also letter of President Truman to His Holiness Pope Pius XII, May 14, 1952, and the Pope's reply July 10, 1952 (Box 6)
- Loose leaf volume of telegrams, news clippings, etc., mainly concerning the illness and death of Pope Pius XII, 1958 (Box 7)
- Exract from meeting of Protestant leaders, 1947-1951 (4 binders) (Box 7)
- Mr. Taylor's contacts with Protestant leaders, 1947-1951 (1 binder) (Box 7)
- Distribution of religious denominations in Europe, Mar. 1949 (1 binder) (Box 7)
- Personal and confidential papers of Hon. Myron Taylor. Includes reports of meetings with Protestant clergymen, Oct. 20, 1947 and May 3, 1949 (1 binder) (Box 7)
- Correspondence between Bishop Oxnam and Myron Taylor, 1940-1945 (1 binder) (Box 7)
- Relations between ecumenical movement and the Vatican in the Twentieth Century. Prepared by Henry Smith Leiper (3 binders) (Box 7)
- Resignation of Hon. Myron Taylor as personal respresentative of the President of the United States of America to His Holiness Pope Pius XII, 1949-1952, including printed copy Jan. 18, 1950 (5 binders) (Box 7)
- Intergovernmental Committee on Political Refugees, 1943-1944. They appear to have different materials (4 binders) (Box 7)
- Refugee file, 1943-1944 (1 binder) (Box 7)
- Post-War Studies Territorial-Refugee Programs, 1943(1 binder) (Box 7)
- Newspaper clippings regarding Mr. Taylor's Resignation...to His Holiness Pope Pius XII (1 binder) (Box 7)
- Loose-leaf volume containing news items regarding his resignation, etc., Jan. 18, 1950 (Box 7)
- Correspondence between Mr. Taylor and the Presidents, 1940-1950 (2 binders, one is incomplete) (Box 7)
- Correspondence with President Truman, May 1951-June 1951(1 binder) (Box 7)
- The Rise of the Double Diplomatic Corps in Rome: A Study of International Practice, by Robert A. Graham, S.J., The Hauge, 1952 (printed pamphlet) (Box 7)
- "Diplomatic Relations between the United States and the Papal States," Resarch Project No. 22, March 1947 (mimeo) (Box 7)
- Volume of typescripts, Intergovmental Committee on Political Refugees - Instructions to Myron Taylor, 1938 (Box 7)
- Volume of mimeo copies of Meetings Officers of the Intergovnmental Committee of Political Refugees, Department of State, Washington, Oct. 17, 1939 (Box 7)
- Proceedings of the Intergovernmental Committee, verbatim record of the Plenary Meetings of the Committee, resolutions and reports, July 1938 (1 bound, printed volume) (Box 7)
- Photograph of Myron C. Taylor (large) by Pirie MacDonald, New York (Box 8)
- Large loose-leaf volume of Vatican Clippings, from various newspapers, 1950 (Box 8)
- Loose-leaf volume of typescript copies of letters relating to the Vatican (Box 8)
- Loose-leaf volume of carbon typescript copies of letters relating to the Vatican, but not the same as above (Box 8)
- Remarks at luncheon arranged by Mr. Taylor at 71, Broadway, New York, Dec. 2, 1932, to further the Share the Work Movement (1 binder) (Box 8)
- Russia - Observations on the present state of American-Soviet relations, Sept. 19, 1951, Myron C. Taylor (2 binders, original typescript and carbon) (Box 8)
- Also entitled Russia, but contains different material from above (1 binder - copies of letters, articles, some original letters) (Box 8)
- Russia, Myron C. Taylor (manilla folder - copies of letters, mimeo and photocopies of articles, all seem to pertain to Russia) (Box 8)
- Texts of Teheran Declarations, Yalta Parley Agreements, Potsdam Agreements as printed on the New York Times, Mar. 25, 1947 (1 binder, news clippings) (Box 8)
- A Survey of Modern Trends in Papal Diplomacy (5 binders, 1 original typescript and 4 carbon copies) (Box 8)
- Correspondence between President Franklin D. Roosevelt and His Holiness Pope Pius XII, 1939-1944 (8 binders, 1 original typescript and 7 carbon copies) (Box 8)
- Loose-leaf volume containing copies of letters on various subjects, many of which are in other books (Box 8)
- Carbon copies of "Reflections on the State, Its Form and Duties," by Prince Rupprecht of Bavaria, written in 1941-1942 (Box 8)
- "Lavenir de l'Autriche" (Mimeo, marked "Copie Nr. US/1 destinee pour Mr. Franklin D. Roosevelt, United States President") Preface states document comprises two separate proposals, one, in French, by Bishop Hudal, and one, in English by B.H. Schilling (Box 8)
- "Austria's Independence," no author, just Rome, Aug. 1944 (mimeo) (Box 8)
- Diplomatic Relations with the Vatican, by Robert A. Graham, S.J. and Robert C. Hartnett, S.J. The American Press (printed pamphlet, Mr. Myron mentioned on 6 pages) (Box 8)
- News supplement, Sunday News, Oct. 13, 1952 (Vatican and Pope Pius XII) (Box 8)
- International Catholic Migration Commission, Sept. 1952 (bulletin) (Box 8)
- Book of Special Letters, Mr. Myron Taylor - Personal. Letters are pasted in and are from well-known people in the United States, Europe, etc., ca. 1925-1956 (Box 8)
  Loose on shelf, too large for box
- Certificates and diplomas, Date unknown (Folder 1)
- Drawing of a chapel, Undated (Folder 2)